בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף Daf is מ"ט. Mem Tet.
We pick up at the משנה Mishnah on the bottom of מ"ח
עמוד ב'. Mem Chet Amud Bet.
For whatever reason I can't really explain the order of the
משניות Mishnayot after dealing with the classic like goring ox and then
we had a sort of a broader we sort of started creating
some broader discussions about questions of doubt, questions about what happens when
you give somebody a right to come into your yard, how much
you're accepting responsibility, which was not just a question of goring, it
was שן, Shein, it was רגל, Regel, it was בור, Bor, it
was sort of everything. And now we get back to the goring
ox and we get back to the case that was referred to
a number of times in the גמרא Gemorrah about the
about in the Torah about two people fighting and a miscarriage and
paying for the דמי ולדות Dmei Vlados for the child for the
loss for the fetus and that that would not apply by the
case of the goring ox. Let's take a look with that in
our משנה Mishnah here at the bottom of מ"ח עמוד ב'. Mem
Chet Amud Bet. שור שהיה מתכוין לחברו והכה את אשה ויצאו ילדיה
פטור מדמי ולדות. Shor shehaya mitkaven lachaveiro vehika et isha veyatzu yeladeha
patur midmei vlados. So an ox was trying to gore its fellow
ox
and accidentally it smote it gored a woman
and it caused her to miscarry. פטור מדמי ולדות. Patur midmei vlados.
The owner of the ox does not have to pay the cost
of the miscarried fetus, the miscarried child. ואדם שהיה מתכוין לחברו והכה
את אשה ויצאו ילדיה משלם דמי ולדות. V'adam shehaya mitkaven lachaveiro vehika
et isha veyatzu yeladeha meshalem dmei vlados. But if two people were
fighting and perhaps somebody's trying to kill ראובן Reuven and accidentally hit
ראובן's Reuven wife and caused her to miscarry, משלם דמי ולדות meshalem
dmei vlados pays the cost of the lost fetus. So the גמרא
Gemorrah is going like there's two points here, why are we only
talking in both of these scenarios about trying to hit somebody else
and hitting the woman? What if he tried to hit the woman?
So in the case of two people fighting, if he tried to
hit the woman, presuming that meant an attempt to kill the woman,
then it would be an issue of קים ליה. Kimlei. But interestingly
it doesn't seem like we say קים ליה Kimlei if he's trying
to hit ראובן Reuven and accidentally hits ראובן's Reuven wife. You know
we discussed before like ממון לזה ומיתה לזה, Mamon lazeh u'misa lazeh,
like to what degree are those when do you say קים ליה
Kimlei do the acts have to be sort of seen in the
same category or not, to be like in the same event or
not. But if he was directly trying to hit the woman and
if it was something that would have possibly brought about her death,
then he wouldn't pay her because of קים ליה. Kimlei. Why the
ox wouldn't have paid, doesn't say it would have paid, but it
sounds like we don't know if the ox was trying to gore
the woman or why the ox why it would have made a
difference. The ox doesn't pay even when it was trying to gore
somebody else. So we'll see in the גמרא Gemorrah what the story
is if the ox is trying to gore the woman. Now how
do you finally we finally get to this question of how do
you pay the דמי ולדות? Dmei Vlados? What does that mean?
כיצד משלם דמי ולדות? Keitzad meshalem dmei vlados? How do you pay
the cost of the child that was miscarried? שמין את האשה כמה
היא יפה עד שלא ילדה וכמה היא יפה משילדה. Shamin et ha'isha
kama hi yafa ad shelo yaleda vekama hi yafa misheyaleda. You see
how much a woman would have gone for in a slave market
as a pregnant woman who had not yet given birth and כמה
היא יפה משילדה kama hi yafa misheyaleda and how much she's worth
now that she's given birth and you pay the difference. Now this
as I
said is very strange that you do this, this is a standard
how you'd assess
נזק Nezek in a case of injury of people, you use the
slave market measure. But what's strange is that you should be exempt
by the case of the ox. Like I really still don't really
understand this, I gotta tell you. Like okay we have a פסוק
Pasuk you know that sort of says כי ינצו אנשים אנשים ולא
שוורים. Ki yintzu anashim, anashim velo shevarim. But it sounds like you
know that fundamentally this is some different different phenomenon. I don't understand
why it's a different phenomenon. The ox injured somebody, caused them an
injury, caused them a loss. On the slave market would have been
worth less. Like why is that not just standard נזק Nezek that
an ox does to a person? It sounds like and we'll see
in the גמרא Gemorrah you know that because
when you'd be paying for this person on the slave market, you
were not and you paid more money you weren't really paying for
this person. Like this slave you know if you think about the
long 30 years I'm gonna own this slave or whatever it is,
like it's not that now I'm paying more because this woman now
as a slave is worth more you know is gonna be worth
more money for me long term in terms of the person. The
injury you're paying because you're getting a bonus, you're getting an extra
baby slave in the package. So therefore the injury really although the
way you assess the value of the baby slave of the fetus
is by looking at the difference in the slave market, it's really
not the difference in value of the slave. What you're really doing
is you're paying the extra money because in the package you're getting
an extra bonus together with the package. Not really נזק Nezek to
the woman. Not נזק Nezek to the woman. Right which is why
it's דמי ולדות. Dmei Vlados. Right exactly. The woman long term is
going to be let's say you know she didn't suffer any trauma
due to this goring, whatever you know and let's say long term
she's just as healthy and just as you know everything as she
would have been beforehand. So there's no real long term damage to
the woman's body. What there was was the loss of this extra
thing which was not really her market price. So therefore that seems
to be the idea, and therefore the idea seems to be that
because this thing, right, it's like, well what did it damage? Like
it didn't damage a it didn't damage a chair, it damaged this,
you know, baby, this unborn baby. Well, who do you pay, who
owns an unborn baby? You know, it's like what, well it's sort
of like a I mean I guess it's like maybe it's a
דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba le'olam property also from like
that, who even owns an unborn baby? Like if you go, right,
and therefore to what degree do you commodify that? Or maybe you're
right, maybe also partly because it's like hidden and it's not even
בעלי עולם. ba'alei olam. So that seems to be why there's more
seen of this חידוש chiddush that there's going to be a payment
here because it's not really injury to the woman's body and it's
injury of this thing and you have to first of all define
who owns it, like who's entitled to payment when this thing gets
lost and that's going to be the husband. And we actually found
out that even if she doesn't have a husband, it's not her,
which is interesting, right, it's not just the husband even like it's
only seen to be the husband. And that it's the whole thing
is a חידוש chiddush that you know maybe because it's a דבר
שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba le'olam maybe because it's a commodifying
of a fetus which we have not yet had and therefore you're
not going to have that payment in the case of an ox.
You're only going to have that payment that the תורה Torah is
מחדש mechadesh it in the case of two people that fight. Okay,
so how do you assess it? You assess the difference in the
slave market. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, אם כן מי
שהאשה יולדת משבחת. im kein mi sheha'isha yoledes meshabbachas. No, because a
woman actually is worth more after she gave birth. Now because he
figures that a woman is in well and I'm going to tell
you what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, is in danger
of losing her wife I mean her life in the process of
childbirth and therefore if you're really assessing the value of the woman,
you know, you know after she's given birth and now she can
go work in the fields and now she's healthy, right, a pregnant
woman she's got who knows be on bedrest or whatever it is,
as a slave, she is worth more after she gave birth, right?
You might not get the free slave out of the deal but
she is worth more. Now of course okay, she is worth more,
but to figure out the value of the baby let's use her
value on the slave market. אלא, Ella, let's see what he says.
שמין את הולדות כמה הן יפין ונותן לבעל. shamin es havelados kama
hein yaffin venosein laba'al. No, you just directly assess the value of
the fetus. How do you do that? Presumably he says you can't
use the slave market because that's going to factor in her value
long term and that actually right now her value is low because
there's a risk she might not survive etc. So I don't know
what you do. You I guess you go around and you ask
people how much would you pay to own an unborn fetus with
the percentage likelihood that it'll be given birth and then it'll be
your slave or something like that. So you don't do it in
terms of the package of the woman, you try to directly assess
how much people would pay for this fetus as a slave. ונותן
לבעל, Venosein laba'al, you give it to the husband. ואם אין לבעל,
Ve'im ein laba'al, if he does not have a husband,
נותן ליורשיו, nosein leyoreshav, you give it to his heirs meaning if
the husband is dead. If she's divorced we had that case before
also that she doesn't get it, nobody gets it.
היתה שפחה ונשתחררה
או גיורת פטור. Haysa shifcha venishtachrera o giyores patur. If however she
was a freed slave or a convert you're exempt. Now why are
you exempt? I mean if she's a freed slave or convert married
to a man, just give it to the man. So the גמרא
Gemara רש״י Rashi there's a long רש״י Rashi whatever it sounds like
the גמרא Gemara assumes and רש״י Rashi explains that it's really not
about her being a freed slave or freed freed slave or a
convert, it's about that she's married to a freed slave or a
convert and therefore if the man dies there are no heirs. So
since the משנה Mishna said a minute ago for heirs you give
to the heirs if the husband is dead but if there is
no husband then you basically that I mean excuse me if there
are no heirs because the husband was a freed slave or convert
and he didn't have children then you obviously then you don't pay.
And the חידוש chiddush about all of this is that you don't
give it to her. Right and that's what's so shocking is that
and that's what really points out the idea that you are considering
this to be some independent entity and somehow something that only the
husband has rights to, that he can bequeath to his kids like
anything else he has money coming in and so on but that
if but that would not transfer to her under any circumstance. Let's
say she's divorced at the time of the injury. We had that
before, right. Now the גמרא Gemara before actually discussed the I should
I think I mentioned before that that divorced would be a case
but I I misspoke because like the גמרא Gemara I have to
double check as the גמרא Gemara discussed right even if they were
even if she gave birth out of wedlock, right? It's בעל האשה,
ba'al ha'isha, it's sort of read it as בועל האשה. bo'el ha'isha.
So it's really the father of the children, not the husband of
the children. So I misspoke a minute ago. So if they she's
not married, you still give it to the father of the children,
but she as the mother has no financial rights to this to
this fetus. Yes Charlie. So that brings the question what if she's
been like licentious or promiscuous and she doesn't know who the father
is? You don't know the father, you don't pay anybody. המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara.
טעמא דנתכוון לחבירו. Taima deniskayvein lachaveiro. So the reason the ox the
it's doesn't pay, the owner of the ox doesn't pay is because
the ox was trying to to gore a different ox.
הא נתכוון לאשה, Ha niskayvein le'isha, one would surmise from the משנה
Mishna that if the ox was directly trying to gore the woman.
משלם דמי ולדות, meshalem dmei vlados, you would pay. לימא תהוי תיובתא
דרב אדא בר אהבה, leima tehvei tiyuvta d'Rav Adda bar Ahava, let's
say this is a contradiction to רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Adda
bar Ahava, דאמר רב אדא בר אהבה, damar Rav Adda bar Ahava,
שוורים שנתכוונו לאישה פטורים מדמי ולדות, shvarim sheniskavnu l'ishah pturim midmei vlados,
that if oxen even if it's trying to gore the woman, it's
exempt because the whole case in the תורה Torah is for people,
not for oxen. It doesn't matter if the ox is or is
not trying to gore, by a person it might matter because of
קים ליה. kim lei. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר לך
רב אדא בר אהבה, amar lach Rav Adda bar Ahava, רב אדא
בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava will say to you, הוא הדין
דאפילו נתכוונו לאישה נמי פטורים. hu hadin d'afilu niskavnu l'ishah nami pturim.
The משנה Mishnah does not mean to exclude the case of trying
to gore the woman. Whether it did or didn't try to gore
the woman, no payment for דמי ולדות dmei vlados for an ox.
נמי פטורים מדמי ולדות. nami pturim midmei vlados. והאי דקתני שור שהיה
מתכוון לחבירו, vehai d'katani shor shehaya miskaven l'chaveiro, so why does it
say it was intending to gore a fellow ox? איידי דקבעי למיתני
aidi d'kabaei l'misni
סיפא, seifa, אדם שהיה מתכוון לחבירו, adam shehaya miskaven l'chaveiro, since it's
going to contrast it to a case of a person who is
trying to hit ראובן Reuven and winds up hitting ראובן's Reuven wife,
דהכי כתיב קרא d'hachi ksiv kra because that's the case in the
תורה, Torah, קתני רישא נמי שור שהיה מתכוון לחבירו, katani reisha nami
shor shehaya miskaven l'chaveiro, so it gives the scenario of trying to
gore one and goring the other, but actually in the case of
the ox it wouldn't matter, you'd be exempted in both. It's also
funny because the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like that even in
the משנה, Mishnah, it really even in the case of people, the
only reason it wrote it that way was because that's what's in
the פסוקים, psukim, sounds like it really wouldn't matter by people, maybe
you would also pay even if you were מתכוון לאישה. miskaven l'ishah.
Now if you were מתכוון לאישה miskaven l'ishah not to kill her,
maybe you would pay, but if you were מתכוון לאישה miskaven l'ishah
in order to kill her, right, then it would be a קים
ליה kim lei case. But it is funny the גמרא Gemara doesn't
even introduce קים ליה, kim lei, just says look, we're just following
the scenario in the תורה, Torah, we do not mean to halachically
limit it just to this case. Okay so now let's continue.
אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, שור שנגח את השפחה ויצאו ילדיה,
shor she'nagach es hashifchah v'yatzyu yeladeha, משלם דמי ולדות. meshalem dmei vlados.
All of this that an ox doesn't pay is when it gores
a free woman. But if it gored a slave and caused a
miscarriage, you would pay. Why?
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? To the owner of the
slave. חמרתא מעברתא בעלמא הוא דאזיל. chamarta m'ubarta b'alma hu d'azil. And
now this is of course very difficult when the גמרא Gemara deals
with some of these comments about non-Jews or about non-Jewish slaves and
so on. It's just, you know, it's just injuring like a donkey,
like a pregnant donkey, meaning the sort of question I had before
which is, I don't understand, the woman was worth more before, worth
more less, why don't you pay it by an ox if you
use the slave market? So the point is well yes, but your
using of the slave market comes
after you're מחדש mchadesh that there is going to be a payment
for a person and we have to find some model to use
to assess a dollar value, right, but if somebody actually lost their
arm, you wouldn't say, oh, you know how much that's worth? Now
you're worth less on the slave market. What do you mean I'm
worth less on the slave market? I was never put on the
slave market to begin with. The use of the slave market as
a way of assessing value is once you say, look, the חידוש
chiddush is you pay for injury. Now we have to find some
type of way of assessing a dollar value to it, let's use
the slave market. That's normally what you say. And therefore you could
say in the case of a lost fetus, the תורה Torah was
never מחדש mchadesh that you pay for a lost fetus, okay, because
you know, and there's so you don't you have to start by
saying you're going to assign a dollar value here to a human
life that fundamentally is not a commodity. The תורה Torah would not
only by a fetus only said that in the case of the
husband, right, or the case of people fighting, not in the case
of an ox fighting. Okay, but what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is if it gores a slave, then it really does start as
a piece of property. This ox damaged something that the owner, you
know, that was a property of the owner, it was also a
human being, but it was also property of the owner. So you
don't need any חידוש chiddush if an ox damages something that's a
piece of property that now it is worth less, so then it's
worth less, it should pay, right? By somebody who's not a slave,
you don't have the initial property model to begin with. So you
have to first say there's going to be a payment
for some loss of limb, there's going to be a payment for
a loss of a fetus, let's look for a model, okay, and
we weren't מחדש mchadesh the loss of a fetus payment by an
ox, but here it starts with the loss of property. All right,
so that seems to be the point. So you don't have to
make some big like sort of like
devaluing of
slaves or whatever, just acknowledging that legally they're property. Of course the
next line in the גמרא Gemara makes all this harder. דאמר קרא,
d'amar kra, שבו לכם פה עם החמור, shvu lachem poh im hachamor,
עם הדומה לחמור. im hadomeh l'chamor. So you see they're just like
donkeys anyway. But I really think the point is is that you
don't need the חידוש chiddush of דמי ולדות dmei vlados if you
start fundamentally with the idea that it's property. Now let's look at
this little תוספות, Tosafot, I saw there was a question but let's
first look at this תוספות. Tosafot. He says חמרתא מעברתא... chamarta m'ubarta...
ואם תאמר v'im tomar הא גבי בור תנן בשלהי פרקין ha gabei
bor t'nan b'shilei pirkin נפל לתוכו עבד או אמה פטור nafal l'tocho
eved o ama patur ואמינא דהוי כחמרתא מעברתא v'amina d'havei k'chamarta m'abarta
ולא נתמעט משור ולא חמור. v'lo nitma'et mishor v'lo chamor. Remember an
ox, a well you're exempt if a human life is lost in
an ox, right? If a human dies in an ox. You don't
pay if a slave dies. You don't say, well, that wasn't a
human life, that was just a donkey. So the Torah says שור
ולא אדם, shor v'lo adam, חמור ולא כלים. chamor v'lo kelim. This
is a חמור. chamor. I'm going to pay for it, right? So
Tosfos says you don't say that. You say it's a human life
and you don't pay for it. ויש לומר דהכא v'yesh lomar d'hacha
לא מידי כתיב lo midei ketiv שור דמי ולדות shor d'mei vlados
אלא במקום שהולדות של בעל ela bimkom shehavlados shel baal דכתיב בעל
האישה d'ketiv baal ha'isha אבל כאן הולדות לאדון aval kan havlados la'adon
דכתיב האישה וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה. d'ketiv ha'isha v'yeladeha tihye l'adoneha. Tosfos says
it's really not based on saying that a slave is a donkey.
It's really based on saying that the Torah's category of
ולדות, vlados, whether you pay for a human or you don't pay
for an ox, is when we're talking about a husband, but when
we're talking about an owner, that's not the case in the Torah.
So Tosfos moves away from the donkey focus and the difference between
husband and owner. And what I would say is exactly what I
said before. We are not saying that a slave is just a
donkey. Oh, it's just a donkey, so even though it's חמור ולא
אדם, chamor v'lo adam, you're still going to pay for it in
a well. No. It's a life, it's a human being, and so
on. But what it is is in addition to being a life
and a human being, is that it's also property. And so by
a בור, bor, you don't pay for humans, end of story. But
by an ox, even though there's no חידוש chiddush that you pay
for דמי ולדות d'mei vlados as a human, as a human life,
right, there also is a reality that property was damaged and therefore
there is going to be the payment by the ox goring the
pregnant slave because it also has the status of property. Yes, Dov,
and then Michael. I have two questions. One is why is צער,
tza'ar, why is this confined to נזק? nezek? We're going to get
to צער tza'ar in the גמרא. Gemara. And then why is the
slave market used as a model for נזק nezek whereas for צער
tza'ar it's like how much would you pay me to chop off
your arm? Right, in other words, that's a different model and also
horrific to think about, but it's more humanizing. You mean, so why
by נזק nezek did we not say how much money would you
take to to instead of having an arm? Well, maybe because the
assumption is that is that is that there's no amount of money
for most people, right? So I mean you could say the same
is true about pain too. There's no amount of money. Look, the
big question also always by pain is how much amount of money
would you pay me in order to endure this pain? For a
lot of people the answer is like, I don't care how much
money you give me, I don't want to endure that pain. Or
sometimes it's like how much money would you pay would you pay
to be saved from this pain? But the problem with that is,
well it depends how much money I have to start with, right?
If I'm a multi-millionaire, the answer is a lot different
than if I'm a poor person. So there's even by the pain
there's like not a really good way to determine, right, but I
think the problem is that by the limb, it's like ironic, but
because by the limb it's like so it's like infinite, then that's
we can't use that amount. So we have to use some amount
that actually does assign a dollar value to it. Yeah, Michael. I
mean, one is I thought pain was not exactly, it's a bit
more nuanced than that. We're going to chop your arm off anyway.
How much would you endure to have it with the anesthetic versus
not? Right. Not not to have your arm chopped off. That's what
I said. How much would you how much would you pay to
endure this pain? I didn't say to have your arm chopped off.
That was exactly the question. But for some people the answer is
nothing. You can't pay me any money in the world to have
to undergo that pain. And the other one was going to say
was the שור ולא אדם. shor v'lo adam. I mean, I think
it's, you know, that model might be a little bit different versus
if you hold people like they're a little bit more conscious and
aware of where they should be going versus why you're exempt for.
Okay, well we'll get to that, but that's and, you know, if
you say someone's a חמור, chamor, yeah, I understand, but I anyway
that's not fine. That's possible, but it's not what I see Tosfos
saying. Tosfos I think exactly saying the point I did, which the
point here is not to dehumanize and to say that we don't
consider this person an אדם, adam, but it's to say we do
recognize that this person is property. So when you're dealing with property,
then it's very different. Then you do pay the owner of the
property the loss of the property. Yes. Say we did have those
markets these days where they sell
people what? They sell their organs. Right. Right. Right. That's true. Okay,
let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: כיצד משמנין
דמי ולדות? keitzad m'shamnin d'mei vlados? How do you assess it? So
the גמרא Gemara says דמי ולדות? d'mei vlados? What are you only
talking about the cost of the fetus? שבח ולדות מבעי ליה. shvach
vlados miba'ei lei. There's also the שבח. shvach. Now what does it
mean? It means apparently from the גמרא Gemara we saw this a
day or two ago,
that because when a somebody is pregnant, not only do you say,
"Oh, I'm buying this pregnant slave, I'm going to get some extra
baby, an extra baby in the deal," but the slave also looks
apparently like this, healthier, fatter. When fat was seen as healthy. Okay.
So therefore that also increases based on perception the value of the
woman. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי קאמר. hacha nami ka'amar.
Fine, that's what it means. כיצד משמנין דמי ולדות ושבח ולדות. keitzad
m'shamnin d'mei vlados v'shvach vlados.
Fine, so when you assess the difference of the woman on the
slave market it includes her price is bumped for two reasons. Bumped,
ha ha. Anyway, because of because of the baby and because she
looks like a stronger, bigger woman.
שמין את האישה כמה היא יפה עד שלא ילדה וכמה היא יפה
משילדה. shamin et ha'isha kama hi yafa ad shelo yal'da v'kama hi
yafa m'sheyal'da. Fine. אמר רבן גמליאל: amar Rabban Gamliel: אם כן משהיא
יולדת משבחת. im ken m'shehi yoledet m'shabachat. מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? What
is he saying?
אמר רבה הכי
קאמר: amar Rabba hachi ka'amar: אישה... isha... What, do you think a
woman goes for a higher amount before than after שתלד? sheteled? Or
a woman משבחת meshabachas לאחר שתלד achar sheteled יותר מקודם שתלד? yoter
mikodem sheteled?
On the slave market she goes for more, again, at least the
woman goes for more, but I mean the, excuse me, the woman
goes for more after she's given birth. So what do you mean
that you pay the difference? Now again, maybe you know, okay, in
terms of the woman she's now, you know, now she can get
back to work, now she's not at risk, but you know you
lost the value of the baby. But that's what he's saying. Looking
at the difference in the slave market for the woman is not
an accurate way of assessing the value of the baby because you're
also factoring in the woman's difference and her value, her value goes
up after she's given birth.
Okay. אלא שמינין את הוולדות ונותנין לבעל. Ela shamnin es havladus venosnin
labaal. You directly
assess like somebody how much would you buy to own these you
know the fetus, you'll pay me now and you'll own it after
it's born assuming that it's born as you know it survives and
so on. And that's how you do it. You directly assess the
market value of the fetus.
תניא נמי הכי. Tanyah nami hachi. We taught a similar ברייתא Braita
that that explained that that's what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel was saying. וכי אשה משבחת קודם שתלד יותר מלאחר שתלד?
Vechi isha meshabachas kodem sheteled yoter meachar sheteled? What, you think she's
worth more before rather than after? והלא אשה משבחת לאחר שתלד יותר
מקודם שתלד. Vehala isha meshabachas achar sheteled yoter mikodem sheteled. She's worth
more after she gave birth than before. אלא שמינין את הוולדות ונותנין
לבעל. Ela shamnin es havladus venosnin labaal. So you directly assess the
value of the ולדות. vlados. Okay. רבא אמר הכי קתני. Rava amar
hachi katani. No, here's what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben
Gamliel is saying. וכי אשה למי שיולדת משבחת. Vechi isha lemi sheyoledes
meshabachas. Right. The language is אישה יולדת משבחת. isha yoledes meshabachas. He
adds the words למי שיולדת. lemi sheyoledes. Does the increase in value
of the woman, meaning again, not the value of the fetus inside
of her but the increase in value that it makes her look
healthier and so on, does that is that a something that the
owner, that the husband, somehow is entitled to? Meaning what it's basically
saying, this is why the גמרא Gemara before introduced the idea of
שבח ולדות. shvach vlados. When you're paying for the difference, you're not
just paying for the value of the fetus, you're paying for the
fact that the woman looks healthier. But רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon Ben Gamliel is saying but the husband isn't entitled to that
increase. The husband is only entitled to the value of the ולד.
vlad. What you've done here is you've packaged, you've wrapped within the
value of the ולד vlad the fact that it looks like the
woman is a bigger, healthier woman and that's not something the husband
should be getting.
למי שיולדת משבחת. Lemi sheyoledes meshabachas. ואין לה עצמה בשבח ולדות כלום.
Ve'ein la atzma beshvach vlados klum. And she's not entitled to the
שבח ולדות, shvach vlados, which is not the cost of the ולדות,
vlados, but her own improvement because of the ולד. vlad. אלא שמינין
את הוולדות ונותנין לבעל. Ela shamnin es havladus venosnin labaal. Fine. You
give the husband the actual cost of the fetus itself. ושבח ולדות,
Veshvach vlados, but the way, the fact that she herself, her price
sort of gone up on the slave market, חולקין, cholkin, they split.
Okay. That now that's interesting. Where do you get the idea of
חולקין? cholkin? Right. Normally you give damage to the person, woman's body
to herself, okay. But here I guess, I mean again I don't
know, you know it's just I guess סברא. svara. It's like, well
since the תורה Torah gave the husband the right to the babies
but normally you give injury to her body to herself and this
is injury to her body or depreciation of her body because of
the babies, so that sort of puts it between the two of
them, so we'll split it between the husband and the woman. Okay,
that seems to be the logic.
Okay.
וחולקין. Vecholkin. ושבח ולדות חולקין. Veshvach vlados cholkin. תניא נמי הכי. Tanyah
nami hachi. We taught similarly. Why wouldn't it be then שבח ולדות
shvach vlados should go to her? That's what I just said. Because
the שבח ולדות shvach vlados is a increase in her value but
it's only because of the babies and the תורה's Torah already told
us that the baby was something that the husband had rights to.
So we have to figure out well who has right to her
temporary increase in value because of the babies? So on the one
hand it's her body, on the other hand it's due to the
babies, so we'll be מסברא, misvara, we'll say חולקין. cholkin. What? I
mean I know there's no פסוק, pasuk, it's just
מסברא. misvara. תניא נמי הכי. Tanyah nami hachi. We taught similarly. אמר
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Amar Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel. וכי אשה למי
שיולדת משבחת ואין לה עצמה בשבח ולדות כלום? Vechi isha lemi sheyoledes
meshabachas ve'ein la atzma beshvach vlados klum?
What, I don't understand, you know, does she have no rights to
her increased value due to the baby? אלא שמין הנזק בפני עצמו.
Ela shamin hanazek bifnei atzmo. Now finally now we get to clarifying
all the payment. Okay, rather you assess the נזק, nezek, meaning let's
say forget the fact that now she's worth less because she doesn't
have babies coming with her or a baby. Maybe she actually suffered
some trauma, maybe she's actually going to be laid up in bed
for months after this thing. So whatever the נזק nezek is you
assess that independently and you pay that to the woman. הצער בפני
עצמו. Hatzaar bifnei atzmo. And the suffering you pay the woman. ושמין
את הוולדות ונותנין לבעל. Veshamin es havladus venosnin labaal. And as far
as the fetus is concerned you pay the husband the cost of
the fetus. ושבח ולדות. Veshvach vlados. And the increase that she had
in terms of her own value due to the baby, חולקין, cholkin,
they split. He gets the צער? tzaar? She gets the צער. tzaar.
Now by the way רש"י Rashi points out to another גמרא Gemara
we'll get to בבא קמא Bava Kamma that even about the נזק
nezek there's some way of splitting it but we're not going to
worry about that now. קשיא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל אדרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. Kashya deRabban Shimon Ben Gamliel aRabban Shimon Ben Gamliel. Now there's
a contradiction of these two ברייתות. Braitas. One ברייתא Braita רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel said that you, let me just
check רש"י, Rashi,
right, because what did the earlier ברייתא Braita say? Oh
because the earlier ברייתא Braita said that she's worth less when she's
pregnant and this ברייתא Braita says there's a שבח ולדות shvach vlados
that they split, that she's worth more. more when she's pregnant. So
which is the story? Is she worth less when she's pregnant or
more when she's pregnant? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
לא קשיא. lo kashya. כאן במבכרת כאן בשאינה מבכרת. kan bimvakeret kan
besheina mevakeret. Question of if it's a first child or not a
first child. If it's a first child she's worth less when she's
pregnant, again not the child cost of the ולד, vlad, her own
cost, her own price, because if it's the first time then the
assumption is that there's a high risk that something could go wrong.
But if she's already successfully had a child and then the body
has proven its durability or whatever and it's used to it and
so on, then apparently the assumed risk is much less and therefore
her price does not go down because she is pregnant. Okay.
ורבנן דאמרי שבח ולדות נמי לבעל מאי טעמא, V'rabanan d'amri shevach vladot
nami l'ba'al mai ta'ama, so the rabbis they only look at one
thing: what was she worth before, what's she worth after? So that
difference
packages together both the cost of the fetus and the increase in
her own market value as a result of her being pregnant. So
it's clear that the rabbis say that the husband is entitled not
only to the value of the fetus but the increase in her
own market value. Where do they get that from?
Okay. ורבנן דאמרי שבח ולדות נמי לבעל מאי טעמא, V'rabanan d'amri shevach
vladot nami l'ba'al mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
כדתניא, k'detanya, like we taught in the
ברייתא. baraita. ויצאו ילדיה, v'yatzu yaldeha, her children were expelled, she miscarried,
איני יודע שהיא הרה, eini yodei'a shehi hara, of course she's pregnant.
מה תלמוד לומר הרה, ma talmud lomar hara, why did it say
that they smote a pregnant woman? It would be a little funny
to say they smote a woman and her children came out without
having told me she was pregnant, but okay. Within מדרש הלכה, midrash
halacha, you didn't have to tell me הרה, hara, I could have
figured that out. למה לך lama lach to tell you, שבח הריון
לבעל, shevach herayon l'ba'al, to tell me the words that הרה hara
includes also any improvement in her own value by virtue of the
pregnancy, not by the fetus but by the pregnancy. Okay. ורבן שמעון
בן גמליאל האי הרה מאי דריש ביה, V'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hai
hara mai darish bei, what does he do with that extra word
הרה? hara? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibayei lei l'kh'detanya, like we've done in
a ברייתא. baraita. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר לעולם אינו חייב עד
שיכנו כנגד בית ההריון, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer l'olam eino chayav
ad sheyakenu kineged beit haherayon, that you only the husband only pays
the woman's husband if she miscarries if she was smitten right opposite
like the womb. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, לא תימא כנגד
בית ההריון ממש, lo teima kineged beit haherayon mamash, we don't need
literally opposite the womb. אלא כל היכא דסליף שחנא, ela kol heicha
d'salif shachna, anywhere on the body that directly would have had some
type of a heat or some type of an impact would have
been felt in the
womb ולד vlad felt by the fetus. לאפוקי יד ורגל דלא, l'apukei
yad v'regel d'lo, if it was hit on the leg or the
arm and then she miscarried not, which is so funny because you
would say I don't get it, you hit her on the arm
and right afterwards she miscarried, it probably is the trauma, but it
seems like it's a question of like גרמא, grama, and maybe this
is also part of what the חידוש chiddush is about the case
of the goring ox, because nobody directly gored the fetus, it was
just the woman that gored, the miscarriage was just how the body
or what that was hit, it was just how the body reacted
afterwards. Well, that's גרמא, grama, that's not נזק, nezek, right? So maybe
that has something to do with why this is seen as a
חידוש chiddush and the ox doesn't pay. So then the גמרא Gemara
of course we didn't say that by the case of the pregnant
slave, but okay. Anyway, so it says like well maybe that's true
would be true if she was hit in a place that was
not directly that somehow the impact of the hit was not directly
felt in the womb even if it somehow led to some psychological
trauma etc. that did lead to it, maybe that's seen as גרמא
grama and not seen as direct injury. Okay, but it does seem
as definitely as a חידוש. chiddush. So what we're saying is there's
definitely a חידוש chiddush that you pay for the ולדות vladot and
it has to do with the commodifying of life and so on,
because why in the case of smiting a slave where it's all
directly seen as property it's not a חידוש chiddush and the ox
pays, but in the case of free people it is seen as
a חידוש, chiddush, so the ox doesn't pay, only humans pay, only
when it's directly כנגד בית ההריון. kineged beit haherayon. And then the
question is how do you assess that value? Do you directly try
to determine the market value of the fetus or do you determine
it based on the difference in terms of the pregnant woman and
the woman who has given birth? Yes. We had an interesting question
in the beginning about the fetuses being treated as independent entities. So
let's say a pregnant woman hit somebody. Right, can't collect from her,
can collect from her? There's no הלכה halacha of מגופו, migupo, none.
No, there's no response, no, they're not a בר חיובא. bar chiyuva.
If she had a thirteen-year-old boy in her womb then maybe we
could talk about it. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אשה שפחה ונשתחררה, Isha shifcha v'nishtachrera,
if she was a slave and she has been freed, which again
for the גמרא Gemara really means that she was married to a
slave and therefore there are not going to be any heirs if
the husband is dead.
או גיורת פטור. o giyoret patur. אמר רבה, amar Rabbah, לא שנו
אלא שחבל בה בחיי הגר ומת הגר, lo shanu ela shechaval bah
bechayei hager u'met hager, that she was injured when her husband the
גר ger was alive and then the גר ger died. So then
there's nobody to inherit the debt that's owed to the גר. ger.
וכיון דחבל בה בחיי הגר זכה בהו הגר, v'keivan d'chaval bah bechayei
hager zacha behu hager, once she was injured while her husband was
alive, the גר ger husband then he has rights, then he's entitled
to the payment.
וכיון דמת הגר זכה בהו מן הגר, v'keivan d'met hager zacha behu
min hager, and then when he dies, the one who did the
injury now because the money is still in his pocket, so he
the same way he could seize the גר's ger property. He could
seize the money that he owes the גר. ger. All right.
אבל חבל בה לאחר מיתת הגר aval chaval bah le'achar mitas hager
let's say the גר ger is dead, okay? So what would be
the story, right? What would be the story if a woman was
injured after her husband was dead? Let's say in a normal case
it would presumably go again, because we said the woman the money
never reverts to the woman, okay, but presumably then it would go
straight to his heirs. If she was injured after the husband or
after the father of the child was dead. What if it is
after the גר ger is dead? וחבל בה לאחר מיתת הגר זכיה
לה איהי בגוויהו v'chaval bah le'achar mitas hager zachya lah ihi b'gavaihu
so finally according to רבא, Rava, רבא Rava is telling me you
know what the woman can eventually get paid for the loss of
her own children. Again this really just shows how much of we're
dealing like in the context of a patriarchy, right? That any payments
for the children only goes to the husband or the father even
and his heirs, the woman is completely the mother's completely cut out
from any payment relating to the children. Okay but at least רבא
Rava says no, if there are no heirs, then it does go
to her, you know? Yes, it's first his, but at least second
it's hers. Not immediately second, after there are no heirs, if he's
a dead גר, ger, then it'll be her. Okay, so that doesn't
apply to the case of a שפחה, shifcha, right? Right. רש"י Rashi
says it's really not about the woman. It's a case of a
שפחה shifcha and a and a גר ger in order to have
a case where there's no no יורש. yoresh. Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so
according to רבא Rava at least it's not a total the patriarchy
does not totally exclude the mother. As long as if there are
no heirs and the injury occurred at the moment when the father
the father was completely out of the picture she would actually collect.
Now what is this regular laws of ירושה yerusha in general? No,
regular laws of ירושה yerusha the mother the wife never collects from
the husband. So it's not about ירושה yerusha here. It's about fundamentally
she's entitled as the mother once you get the father and his
and his heirs out of the picture. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. אבל חבל בה וכו' זכיה לה איהי בגוויהו
ומחייב לשלומי לה לדידה aval chaval bah v'chu zachya lah ihi b'gavaihu
u'mechayev l'shalumei lah l'didah and he has you have to pay her.
אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda מרי דהאי mari dehai the master
of this discussion, meaning like it's a sort like it's some type
of you know of like what are you talking about? Okay. אטו
ולדות צרוני נינהו atu vladot tzaronei ninhu what, you think that the
fetus is like a little bundle of
money, a little bundle of joy? It's funny, צרוני tzaronei is a
bundle. Anyway.
וזכי בהו v'zachi behu and she like somebody owns the child, meaning
he's basically saying, you know, you don't own your children, okay? So
the whole idea, well if there's no husband then the mother what
do you mean? It's not there's not a concept here of like
fundamentally being owned and you damaged my property or things that I
own. אלא איתיה לבעל זכיה ליה רחמנא ליתיה לבעל לא ella isei
l'ba'al zachya leh rachmana lisei l'ba'al lo it's just an arbitrary assignment
monetary award not reward, award that the תורה Torah signs, but there's
not a question of owning the baby, owning the fetus. So therefore
the תורה Torah is מחדש mechadesh that if there's a husband he
gets some payment, it was never מחדש mechadesh that a woman gets
the payment. If you look at it not as a compensation for
a loss, but you look at it as some payment the תורה
Torah signs, the the תורה Torah just only didn't assign it in
this case, end of story. Okay? So it's not like he fundamentally
disagrees that like the mother, you know, has rights to her baby,
but what he's doing is he's questioning the idea of ownership of
the baby all together. Okay if you look at it as a
type of an ownership you could say when the husband and his
heirs are out of the picture the mother owns the baby. But
he says I just look at it as an assigned payment and
if therefore if there's no חדוש chidush then there's nothing to pay,
which is also why I guess you don't pay in the case
of a שור. shor. Okay so he says like this. But רבא
Rava still holds his position. And we're going to focus on רבא's
Rava position. מתיבי Meisivei I'll ask you, now we're going to try
to challenge רבא's Rava idea that the mother does get paid. הכה
את האשה ויצאו ילדיה נותן נזק וצער לאשה ודמי ולדות לבעל Hakeh
es ha'ishah v'yatze'u yeladeha nosen nezek v'tza'ar la'ishah u'dmei vladot l'ba'al
you smite a woman and she miscarries, you pay the נזק nezek
and the צער tza'ar to the woman like we said because of
just her own injury and the cost of the ולדות vladot to
the husband. אין הבעל נותן ליורשיו Ein haba'al nosen l'yorshav if the
husband is not around you pay to his heirs. אין האשה נותן
ליורשיה Ein ha'ishah nosen l'yorsheha if the woman isn't around you pay
the payments that would normally go to her to her heirs. היתה
שפחה ונשתחררה או גיורת Haysa shifcha v'nishtachrara o giyores however
if she was again שפחה shifcha which we are saying means married
to a גר ger and the גר ger isn't around, זכה zachah
so the person who owes the money, you know, wins out, he
doesn't have to pay. And we're assuming this means even if there
was no husband, the גר ger had already been dead when the
injury occurred. So you see that you see רבא's Rava wrong, you
don't pay the woman. אמר ליה Amar lei the answer is ומי
עדיפא ממתניתין u'mi adifa mimatanisin why is that any better of a
question than our משנה? Mishnah? דאוקימנא דחבל בה בחיי גר ומית גר
de'ukimna d'chaval bah b'chayei ger u'meis ger we said the משנה Mishnah
is talking about that the injury occurred when the גר ger was
alive and then he died. הכא נמי דחבל בה בחיי גר ומית
גר hacha nami d'chaval bah b'chayei ger u'meis ger here too where
there's no payment it's when the injury occurred when the גר ger
was around and then he died and there's no one to inherit.
But if the גר ger was if the husband גר ger had
died before the injury you would pay the mother according to רבא.
Rava. ואיבעית אימא לאחר מיתת הגר v'iba'is eima le'achar mitas hager or
I could tell you that yes, the injury occurred after the גר
ger died. ותני זכה v'sani zachah gets paid, and when it says
זכתה, zachsa, it doesn't mean זכה zacha the one who would pay,
זכתה zachsa means the one that the one who's deserved to be
paid gets paid, the woman gets paid. Okay, so רבה's Rabba still
insisting though that if the גר ger if the husband and his
heirs are completely out of the picture, the woman, the mother actually
gets paid. לימא כתנאי. Leima kitanna'ei. Let's say this is connected to
a debate of תנאי, tanna'ei, or this is a debate of תנאי.
tanna'ei. בת ישראל שניסת לגר. Bat Yisrael shenis'ess leger.
So here finally this ברייתא braisa discusses it directly, not with a
free slave woman, but by a normal woman, whatever, who was married
to a גר. ger. Okay, בת ישראל bat Yisrael was married to
a גר, ger, ונתעברה ממנו venis'abra mimenu and has a baby and
is pregnant. וחבל בה בחיי הגר, Vechaval ba bechayei hager, and she's
injured by this person in the life of the גר, ger, נותן
דמי ולדות לגר. nosein dmei vlados leger.
So he pays to the husband. לאחר מיתת הגר. Le'achar misas hager.
So now what happens though if she was injured after the גר
ger died? תני חדא חייב, Tani chada chayav,
so one ברייתא braisa says if she suffered the injury after her
husband the גר ger was dead and there were no heirs, it
says that you still have to pay her. ותני חדא פטור, Vetani
chada patur, another ברייתא braisa says you don't pay her. So that
seems to be exactly our debate, right? Does she get it if
there was no גר ger husband around when when the injury occurred?
מאי לאו תנאי נינהו, Mai lav tanna'ei ninhu, doesn't isn't it a
debate of תנאי? tanna'ei? That רבה, Rabba, so לדרבה ודאי תנאי היא.
le-Rabba vadai tanna'ei hi. So okay, you're right, for רבה Rabba it's
definitely a debate of תנאי. tanna'ei. לתנא דאמר חייב, Le-tanna de-amar chayav,
you still have to pay the you pay the mother in that
case, הוי כרבה, hovei ke-Rabba, ולמאן דאמר פטור ve-liman de-amar patur says
disagrees with רבה. Rabba. So fine. אלא לרב חסדא מי לימא תנאי
היא, Ella le-Rav Chisda mi leima tanna'ei hi, would you say according
to רב חסדא Rav Chisda who says that you never pay the
mother, would you say that's a debate of תנאי? tanna'ei? Because here
you got a ברייתא braisa that says you do pay. לא קשיא,
Lo kashya,
no it's not difficult. הא רבנן והא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Ha
Rabbanan ve-ha Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. The debate here is not paying
for the ולדות. vlados. You would never pay for the ולדות vlados
according to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. You would never pay the mother
for the ולדות. vlados. The question is is paying for the שבח
ולדות? shevach vlados? Okay, for the depreciation in her own value because
of now she's no longer pregnant, not because of the ולד. vlad.
Okay, so one would say, now remember, who gets the שבח ולדות?
shevach vlados? You remember this? The רבנן Rabbanan say the husband gets
it, and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says she
gets half. Okay, so here he's saying this debate when there's no
husband, no גר, ger, he's dead, no heirs, etc., do you pay
her? רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, I would say that paying for
the ולדות vlados you never pay her. That's my position. The debate
is about paying for the שבח ולדות, shevach vlados, that according to
one you do pay her, because according to one, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said she always gets paid for partly
at least for the שבח ולדות. shevach vlados. And according to the
other opinion you don't, because you only the husband that gets the
שבח ולדות. shevach vlados. Okay, so for the שבח ולדות shevach vlados
I agree she could get paid. For the ולדות vlados she will
not get paid. הא רבנן והא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Ha Rabbanan
ve-ha Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So the Gemara says one minute, אי
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל מאי איריא לאחר מיתה אפילו מחיים נמי אית
לה פלגא. i Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel mai irya le'achar misas afilu
mechayay nami iss lah palga. One minute, according to רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that she's getting paid, but she was
getting half paid even when her husband was alive. You didn't need
her husband to be a dead גר ger to get her receiving
payment for the
שבח ולדות. shevach vlados. So the Gemara says, מחיים אית לה פלגא.
mechayay iss lah palga. You're right, but when her husband was alive,
she only took half of the שבח ולדות shevach vlados and her
husband took the other half. לאחר מיתה כולה. Le'achar misah kullah. Afterwards
she gets all of it. Now, of course the question that you
should be asking me is one minute, why does she get the
other half of her שבח ולדות shevach vlados when the husband is
out of the picture, but she's not going to get the value
of the ולד vlad when the husband is out of the picture.
Everybody with me what we're saying? According to רב חסדא Rav Chisda
we're saying that when the husband is out of the picture the
mother never gets the value of the ולד. vlad. But if she
was getting half of the שבח ולד shevach vlad according to רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, she'd get all of it
after the husband is out of the picture. Because the ולד vlad
is not hers so to speak. Well, that's what he's going to
say. The ולד vlad is something that's nobody owns the ולד. vlad.
Right,
so that's what the Gemara's going to say. Nobody owns the ולד,
vlad, it was just an assignment of a payment in the Torah.
If there's no husband, the Torah never assigned payment. שבח ולד shevach
vlad is an actual that is her body, and that is an
actual loss that came to her, and she actually always had a
right to it, she was just sharing that value with the husband.
So then she's entitled to all of it when the husband isn't
around. So that's what we're going to get to say. Okay, let's
just let's now say that. ואיבעית אימא הא והא רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. ve'iba'is eima ha ve-ha Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. This question about
do you pay the mother both is רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel when there's no husband, it's a dead גר, ger,
etc. כאן בשבח ולדות כאן בדמי ולדות. Kan be-shevach vlados kan be-dmei
vlados. It's exactly this difference. You do pay the mother the שבח
ולדות, shevach vlados, you don't pay the mother even if the husband
is dead and he's a גר, ger, etc., you don't pay the
mother the דמי ולדות, dmei vlados, the value of the fetus itself.
אמרי, Amri, so the Gemara says one minute, משבח ולדות נשמע דמי
ולדות. mishvach vlados lishmo dmei vlados. Let's say this, if you're paying
the mother for the שבח ולדות, shevach vlados, then why not also
say you should pay her for the... you of the ולד velad
itself. And מרבן גמליאל נשמע לרבנן, mi-Rabban Gamliel nishma le-Rabbanan, if you're
doing this payment for רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, you should do it
for the רבנן. Rabbanan. Once you're conceding that the mother gets an
award, gets, you know, payment after the husband is out of the
picture, if what she's doing is she's getting the other half of
the שבח ולדות shevach veladot after the husband is out of the
picture, logically say she should get paid for the דמי ולדות demei
veladot after the husband is out of the picture. But says no,
אמרי לא, amri lo, that's not a good comparison.
שבח ולדות shvach veladot דשייך
ידה בגוייהו, de-shaich yadah be-gavaihu, the שבח ולדות shvach veladot she has
her hand is, you know, connected to it, meaning like she's already
got rights to it even as alive, she had half of it,
or you could just say
technically she was awarded half of it when the husband was alive.
But also B, it's her body. So in that case זכי בהו
בכולהו, zachi behu be-kuleihu, when the husband's out of the picture, she
now has full rights to it. Okay, but that's a real thing
that she had rights to and it's really her body. דמי ולדות,
demei veladot, the actual cost of the fetus itself, דלא שייך ידה
בגוייהו, de-lo shaich yadah be-gavaihu, when the husband was alive she had
nothing, and not only that, according to this logic it's not צרורי,
tzrori, right? It's not like a thing that you own, it's not
your body. So therefore לא זכי בהו כלל, lo zachi behu klal,
she gets nothing if the husband is out of the picture. So
it's a really fascinating question about whether, you know, when the Torah
here, I mean it's a bit of a problem, like the same
way when we have to assess a value of how do you
determine the value of an arm and we say you do the
slave market, and to some degree there we know that that's an
arbitrary assignment of value, but when the Torah says you pay for
the loss of the fetus, it like does raise a question: is
the Torah
conceptualizing this as your child is something that you own and that
you're being paid for the loss of your child? And you know,
so there's like this powerful statement that רב חסדא Rav Chisda is
making. On the one hand it's not great because he cuts the
mother out completely. Okay, but on the other hand what he is
saying is this is not like some type of a thing that
is owned, that you say oh, if the father isn't around, well
the mother gets paid for it. Yes. And how does this play
with the thing
in יבמות Yevamot about עובר ירך אמו, u-bar yerech imo, so this
fetus is like a limb? Right, so עובר ירך אמו, u-bar yerech
imo, and if a woman converts, it's like the טבילה tevilah occurred
on this thing itself. Right, so yeah, you know, I mean I
just don't know what to say about that. Like it's sort of
like what the גמרא gemara said before about
the שפחה. shifcha. Like why is this whole thing a חידוש? chiddush?
This is now a part of her body and that should increase
her value on the slave market, you know, and so on. But
it conceptualizes it really as a limb, right? It's not even it's
nothing else. Right. Yeah, like I'm right, which does get back to
like let's just look at this like this is all her body,
it's a temporary increase in her body, right? If a woman had
grown some extra limb which was going to drop off but then
had some market value, right, you would say now it's part of
her body and if that's her current value in the slave market
she should be, you know, benefit from it. Yeah, I don't know,
I mean again that's sort of, you know, that's get, that's like
I think if we would totally just commodify her and see her
as property we would say that and that's what the גמרא gemara
said about the שפחה, shifcha, but because we're at the same time
like looking at her as a human and this thing is a
future human, but it does raise that question in general like when
do we apply עובר ירך אמו u-bar yerech imo and when do
we say this is a future human that's about going to be
born and has some independence? Yeah, but we again, but it doesn't
but there is a question about, look, the biggest question is, you
know, about the abortion question, right, which is really like: is this
a future life or is this my body, I can do what
I want with my body? In a way that's the question. עובר
ירך אמו, u-bar yerech imo, I just am going to look at
this as my body and as nothing else, or no, it's both
your body and there's a life here that's going to be that's
dependent on you but that's going to become an independent life. So
when הלכה halakha for example, when there are opinions in הלכה halakha
that allow abortion under certain circumstances, is that because we פוסקין paskin
עובר ירך אמו u-bar yerech imo or is that under what? No,
no, no, that's an extreme circumstance when the mother's life is at
risk. But there are actually פוסקים poskim that say you need a
much less threshold to allow for an abortion especially at earlier stages
and so on. Is that because of עובר ירך אמו u-bar yerech
imo or is it no, עובר ירך אמו u-bar yerech imo doesn't
make a difference, it might be part of her body but it's
also a life, you have to assess it on those terms as
well? Right, so that's always like that question about how to look
at it. But yeah, you're right to be raising that question. Yeah,
and also the language דשייך ידה בגוייהו de-shaich yadah be-gavaihu means like
inside, right, you're hand-in-hand. Well, that is true. I mean, that's the
standard language but yes, right, using contemporary terminology that you know
you got your hand in it. Yeah, right, it's true, yeah, exactly.
Yeah, one thing that is not mentioned here is the position that
the Catholic Church has which is that an abortion is actually ממש
mamash murder. Well, yeah, but we're not dealing with abortion here, but
that's correct, although we do say that that's true for בני נח.
bnei noach. Yes. But here
just here
there's no discussion about the possibility you might put the ox on
trial for murder, you might put the, well the ox is stoned,
I mean that's the point. But I mean, oh you mean by
case of miscarriage, it's not. That's correct. Okay. Now, because we're discussing
who gets the things that are owed to a גר ger when
a גר ger dies, we're going to have a nice little digression
about that and put the whole goring ox and the pregnant woman
thing aside for a moment. Okay. בעי מיניה רב ייבא סבא מרב
נחמן. Ba'ei minei Rav Yeiva Sava mi'Rav Nachman. רב ייבא סבא Rav
Yeiva Sava asked רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: המחזיק בשטרותיו של גר מהו
Hamachzik b'shtarotav shel ger, mahu?
Okay,
so basically, a גר ger has in his possession, you know, some
IOUs, right? Says that Charlie owes him a thousand dollars, and therefore
the גר ger dies, I run into the גר's ger house and
I grab his IOUs that Charlie owes him a thousand dollars. Now
of course, I haven't grabbed the debt, I've just grabbed the document.
Charlie is not going to have to pay me a thousand dollars
because I happen to have grabbed the גר's ger שטר shtar after
he died that says that Charlie owed him a thousand dollars. The
question is, so that's taken for granted, Charlie doesn't have to pay
me the money. You know who grabbed Charlie's debt as soon as
the גר ger died? Charlie. Charlie owed him the money, he was
in possession essentially, conceptually, of the money that belonged to the גר,
ger, the גר ger died, you now don't have to pay the
גר. ger. So a גר ger who doesn't have heirs is the
right person to be borrowing money from. Okay. Now, the question is,
I grabbed the piece of
paper. Do I at least get to keep the piece of paper?
That's the question. Or when I grabbed it, I wasn't thinking to
keep a piece of paper, I thought I would get the debt,
and that was my only intent, I really never even took possession
of it qua a piece of paper. That's the question. Okay. So
it says, המחזיק בשטרותיו של גר מהו Hamachzik b'shtarotav shel ger, mahu?
מאן דמחזיק בשטרא אדעתא דארעא דמחזיק. Man d'machzik b'shtara ada'ata d'ar'a d'machzik.
The one who's grabbing the document is grabbing because he thinks it's
going to entitle him to the land that the document has liens
on, which it doesn't, but that's what he thinks. ושטרא נמי לא
קנה
דלאו אדעתא דשטרא. U'shtar nami lo kana d'lav ada'ata d'shtara. And you
don't even get the physical document because you were really just trying
to seize the debt. You weren't trying to seize to own the
document, a piece of paper. או דלמא, Odilma, or do we say,
נמי אדעתא דשטרא, nami ada'ata d'shtara, you also wanted the document? I
would say that that's true, like even if I thought I was
seizing the debt, I knew that in order to collect the debt
I'd have to own the piece of paper, right? So to me,
like, isn't that obvious? Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה אני
מורי. Amar lei, ani mori. Answer me, my
master. וכי לבציצו צריך V'chi l'vatzitzu tzarich? What, does he need this
piece of paper, what, he wants to use it as a bottle
stopper? Like what type of silly question is this? Who needs a
piece of paper? אמר ליה אין רוצו ורוצו. Amar lei, ein, rotzo
v'rotzo. Yes, he wants to use it as a bottle stopper. Meaning,
I don't know why he wants the piece of paper, but that's
my question: does he own the piece of paper?
Okay. So we didn't answer, but presumably, yeah, he does own the
piece of paper. Presumably. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. So now Rava has
a fine question. משכונו של ישראל
ביד גר. Mashkono shel Yisrael b'yad ger. Okay, now, Charlie owes this
גר ger here a thousand dollars. Now Charlie is the one who
owed him that money before. Okay, but the גר ger has in
his
possession Charlie's big screen TV, okay, which he has as a collateral,
okay. And now the גר ger dies. Can I run into the
גר's ger house and seize Charlie's big screen TV?
What do you think? No. Right? As soon as... he had a
שיבודיה shibudei on it, but as soon as the גר ger dies,
it presumably reverts to Charlie. It's Charlie's TV. Okay. So, משכונו של
ישראל ביד גר ומת הגר ובא ישראל אחר והחזיק
בה. Mashkono shel Yisrael b'yad ger, u'meit hager, u'va Yisrael acher v'hechzik
bah. If I went into the גר's ger house after he died
and I seized the big screen TV, מוציאין אותו מידו. motzi'in oto
mi'yado. You take it away from me and you give it back
to Charlie. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama? כיון דמית גר פקע ליה שיבודיה.
Keivan d'meit ger, paka lei shibudei. Once the גר ger dies, his
lien on this משכון, mashkon, on this collateral, disappeared, and therefore it
reverted to its original owner. Okay, now, משכונו של גר ביד ישראל.
Mashkono shel ger b'yad Yisrael. Now it's the reverse. This גר ger
owes Charlie a thousand dollars, and Charlie's got the גר's ger big
screen TV. And then the גר ger dies. Okay. So, does Charlie
have to do a new קנין kinyan on it, or because he
had a lien on it, he owns it right away? That's the
question. Okay. So, ומת הגר ובא ישראל אחר והחזיק
בה. U'meit hager, u'va Yisrael acher v'hechzik bah. So I break into
Charlie's house and I grab the TV that was the collateral. Okay,
so the הלכה halacha is, זה קנה כנגד מעותיו וזה קנה את
השאר. zeh kana k'neged ma'otav, v'zeh kana et hash'ar. So Charlie owns
a thousand dollars of the big screen TV, okay, because that was
the debt. And presumably even without doing a קנין, kinyan, as soon
as the גר ger went away, his liens were exercised, you know,
were actualized, and he now became owner of it
corresponding to the money he was owed. But he didn't own the
rest of it. I took possession of the rest of it. Now
the question is going to be: But I don't understand, it was
in Charlie's house, then he should have just taken possession of it
because it was a piece of the גר's ger property. Forget the
liens! It was in his house and he should just קונה konei
it automatically like a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So let's take a
look. ואמאי, V'amai, says the גמרא, Gemara, תקני ליה
חצירו? tiknei lei chatzero? Let Charlie's yard just automatically take possession. It's
like a הפקר hefker object that's in Charlie's yard. Forget about his
liens, right? He should take possession before I seize it. דאמר רבי
יוסי בר חנינא חצירו של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו. D'amar Rabbi
Yosi bar Hanina: Chatzero shel adam kona lo shelo mida'ato. The yard
takes possession even without his awareness, even if he wasn't aware that
the גר ger had died. אמרי הכא במאי עסקינן. Amri, hacha b'mai
askinan.
that
Charlie is not in the city, he's not in his home, and
the basic principle is that a חצר chatzer only קונה koneh without
the owner's presence if it's a חצר המשתמר. chatzer hamishtamer. If it's
protected. But for instance in the house, house isn't a good example,
the house is משתמר. mishtamer. But let's say it's his front yard.
And he doesn't have a fence around his front yard and anybody
can come and grab it. So if Charlie is not around, the
חצר chatzer doesn't operate. It doesn't operate as a חצר, chatzer, he
still owns the portion of the TV opposite his lawn, the thousand
dollars, 'cause he had those liens on it. He had that right
to it and those rights became actualized when the גר ger died.
But he's not קונה koneh it in the- the rest of it
just 'cause it's in his yard 'cause the yard is not protected
and Charlie is not around. So the rest of it is still
up for grabs and I was able to take possession of the
balance of it that was not opposite the loan that was owed
to Charlie. Okay. Isn't it like something of yours on your front
yard, you're out of town and there's no- there's no fence? Correct.
Exactly. No, no, no. If it's yours, it's yours. If a הפקר
hefker object rolls into your yard or a גר's ger's object was
in your yard and the גר ger died and there's no fence
around it then first come first serve. אמרי, amri, so the גמרא
gemara says, okay, so why didn't- so הכא במאי עסקינן דליתיה, hacha
b'mai iskinan d'leise, Charlie isn't around and therefore his yard doesn't take
possession of it and the balance of it that's not כנגד keneged
the loan, anybody else can take. Okay. כל היכא דאיתיה לדידיה דאי
בעי מקני מצי קני קנייה ליה נמי חצרו. kol heicha d'ise l'didei
d'ei bei maknei matzi kani kanyei lei nami chatzaro.
Anytime he's around where he wanted to take possession he could, so
then his yard takes possession for him. כל היכא דליתיה לדידיה דאי
בעי למיקני לא מצי קני חצרו נמי לא קנייה, kol heicha d'leise
l'didei d'ei bei l'miknei lo matzi kani chatzaro nami lo kanyei, but
if he's not around that if he wanted to take possession he
couldn't, his yard also doesn't. It's funny that it has that very
drawn out language. It could have just said if it's a חצר
שאינה משתמרת, chatzer she'eina mishtameret, you know, and if he's not around
it doesn't work. But anyway, that seems to be the point. And
the גמרא gemara says והוזקקנו להלכה זו דליתיה בחצר דלא קני. v'huzkaknu
l'halacha zo d'leise b'chatzer d'lo kani. You know why it didn't work?
Because- right- again there's two ways of reading this. תוספות tosafot reads
it's just repeating what we just said. Since Charlie isn't in his
yard, he did not take possession of the whole object, he only
took possession of it כנגד keneged his loan, so he only owns
a thousand dollars and anybody else could take possession of the rest
'cause Charlie isn't in his yard. But if Charlie were in his
yard, yes, or if it was- had a fence around it, of
course he would take possession of it fully. רש"י rashi reads דליתיה
d'leise doesn't mean Charlie isn't in the yard, it means the object
isn't in the yard. The big screen TV was somewhere, I don't
know, Charlie had left it in somebody else's, you know, possession or
whatever, it was in the- he had left it in the middle
of the street, so in that case his yard can't take possession
but he automatically owns the part that is opposite his loan and
the rest is free for grabs. Yes, Sol, you had a question?
So I mean, it goes into a question of like, קנין שלא
מדעתו kinyan shelo m'da'ato or like אמר זכי amar zachie and like
זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin l'adam shelo b'fanav, right. Right. So that's
why the language is strange. If he was here he could, if
he wanted to, like- right, right. So that's why תוספות tosafot immediately
just connects this to the idea of חצר משתמרת. chatzer mishtameret. Now
could be that that's why רש"י, rashi, because it is such a
strange language that we normally don't talk in those terms, understands that
the גמרא gemara in the last three words is rejecting everything it
said before. Forget this nonsense about where Charlie is, that doesn't make
a difference. A חצר chatzer is always קונה. koneh. So the case
is that the object wasn't in the חצר, chatzer, that's what we're
talking about. That could be why רש"י rashi reads it that way
'cause the language, it's not that the law is wrong but the
way it's phrasing it is so funny. It should have just said
הכא במאי עסקינן בחצר שאינה משתמרת, hacha b'mai iskinan b'chatzer she'eina mishtameret,
you know, or something like that. Right. So I- I agree with
you. That presumably is why רש"י rashi reads that the last three
words in the גמרא gemara rejects all the stuff that was said
before. And then even- even to push further, but didn't we know
that it's- it automatically falls into his חצר, chatzer, it's immediately... Well,
no, actually it's not a זכות, zchus, but it's... there's a what?
Then we don't assume it's a זכות zchus by גט get but
there's an issue of ידו yado and whatever, ובעל כרחה, u'baal korcha,
right. Right. חצר chatzer is immediately קונה. koneh. Yeah, yeah, yeah, that
is true. But anyway, so that's presumably why רש"י rashi reads the
last three lines- say forget about where Charlie is, the question is
where the object is. That's how רש"י rashi reads the last three-
three words. Okay, let's now start. So now that we've gone through,
I guess wrap-up stuff about goring oxen, we're now finally shifting to
discuss בור bor in a more focused way. So let's at least
get started. החופר בור ברשות היחיד ופתחו לרשות הרבים. hachofer bor b'reshus
hayachid u'pischu l'reshus harabim.
You dig a בור bor in your domain but the opening is
in the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So basically the key here is
looking at this- look at this tiny תוספות. tosafot. החופר בור ברשות
היחיד ופתחו לרשות הרבים. hachofer bor b'reshus hayachid u'pischu l'reshus harabim. תוספות
tosafot
says כללא דמילתא דבכל הך שמעתתא, klala d'milsa d'bechol hach shmaatsa, the
basic rule you have to know about this whole discussion is בור
בתר פיתחו אזלינן. bor basar pischu azlinan. Okay, the-
the well is it goes by where the opening is, right, where
you can fall into it. Okay. דנחשב הבור כאילו במקום שהפתח שם.
d'nechshav habor k'ilu b'makom shehapesach sham.
It's like it's determined by where- by where the opening is. So
basically you have here, here's your רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, right, and
here's the main street, here's the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay. And
you've got your בור- bor well actually that's not a good way
of drawing it or at least whatever, I can't figure out how
to draw it. Okay, anyway, here is the- above the ground. Here's
your רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Okay. And so the under the ground
it goes into רשות היחיד, Reshut HaYachid, it's in your domain, okay,
but the opening is in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabbim, right? Somebody walking
in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabbim is going to fall down. It doesn't
matter that underground it's like in your, it's a dug, you know,
underground it's in your domain, right? Above the ground the opening is
in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabbim, okay? So it goes by where the
opening is. הכופר בור ברשות היחיד ופתחו לרשות הרבים, HaChopher bor bi-reshut
hayachid u-pitcho lirshut harabim, so if it's opened into רשות היחיד, Reshut
HaYachid, or it's dug in רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid but it's open
to רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabbim, או ברשות הרבים ופתחו לרשות היחיד, o
bi-reshut harabim u-pitcho lirshut hayachid, or the reverse, ברשות היחיד ופתחו לרשות
היחיד אחר, bi-reshut hayachid u-pitcho lirshut hayachid acher, or it's both dug
and opened into רשות היחיד אחר, Reshut HaYachid acher, a different רשות
היחיד, Reshut HaYachid, right? He says it means of a different person,
but it just could mean your own רשות היחיד, Reshut HaYachid, a
different one, חייב. chayav. In all these cases it's חייב, chayav, which
basically means that if we're going to assume that it really just
matters where the opening is, what it's basically saying is it doesn't
matter if you dug it in your domain or in רשות הרבים,
Reshut HaRabbim, you're always going to be חייב. chayav. Now when you
dig a בור bor in your domain, you're not חייב chayav if
it's in the middle of my yard, I'm not חייב chayav if
you walk into my yard, okay, especially if you walk in שלא
ברשות. she-lo birshut. The only way you're חייב chayav if it's in
your domain is if you dig it right at the edge of
your property, okay? And then somebody falls in, because then you could
say you did not have a right to walk up to the
edge. I'm sorry, if you are חייב chayav it's because by digging
it right at the edge of your property, right near רשות הרבים,
Reshut HaRabbim, you're creating a hazard for רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabbim. Or
the other scenario is you dig it in the middle of your
property and then you're מפקיר maphker your property
to the רבים, rabbim, and you're giving them access to it. So
if they have access to it because it's right at the edge
or because you've given them access to it, those could be scenarios
that you're חייב chayav for a בור bor in רשות היחיד. Reshut
HaYachid. What we're going to look at tomorrow though is a whole
debate between רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, which
is maybe you're only חייב chayav for one of those two cases.
There's a reason to only be חייב chayav for a רשות הרבים
Reshut HaRabbim for the obvious reason that it's a big public hazard,
as opposed to even the cases I gave by רשות היחיד Reshut
HaYachid it's much less of a hazard. And ironically, there'll be a
reason to be חייב chayav only in רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid. Can
you think why you would be חייב chayav only in רשות היחיד?
Reshut HaYachid?
There's not a good normal logic, but once you've been learning בבא
קמא Bava Kamma you could understand the logic. Because if it's in
רשות היחיד, Reshut HaYachid, then it's yours and you own it. So
in the logic of ממון המזיק, mamon hamazik, right, there's more of
a reason to be חייב chayav assuming that it's also a hazard,
it's at let's say the edge of רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabbim, you
could understand why there's more of a logic in the formalistic logic
of בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Okay, so we'll continue with that tomorrow.
How do you let's say the בור bor